In my early days as a graduate student,
في أيامي الأولى كطالبة متخرجة
I went on a snorkeling trip off the coast of the Bahamas.
ذهبت في رحلة غوص بساحل باهاماس
I'd actually never swum in the ocean before,
في الحقيقة لم أسبح في محيط من قبل
so it was a bit terrifying.
لذا فقد كان الأمر مرعب قليلا
What I remember the most is, as I put my head in the water
أكثر شئ أذكره، هو عندما وضعت رأسي في الماء
and I was trying really hard to breathe through the snorkel,
و كنت أحاول جاهدة أن أتنفس من خلال أنبوب التنفس
this huge group of striped yellow and black fish
هذة المجموعة العملاقة من الأسماك المخططة بالأصفر والأسود
came straight at me ...
أتت باتجاهي...
and I just froze.
و قد تجمتْ
And then, as if it had suddenly changed its mind,
ثم، وكأنها قد غيرت رأيها فجأة
came towards me and then swerved to the right
أتت باتجاهي ثم انحرفت نحو اليمين
and went right around me.
و ذهبت من حولي
It was absolutely mesmerizing.
لقد كان الأمر مذهلا جدا
Maybe many of you have had this experience.
ربما الكثير منكم مروا بهذه التجربة
Of course, there's the color and the beauty of it,
طبعا، هناك اللون و جماله
but there was also just the sheer oneness of it,
و لكن كان هناك أيضا هذا الإتحاد التام
as if it wasn't hundreds of fish
و كأنه لم يكن هناك المئات من الأسماك
but a single entity with a single collective mind
و إنما كيان واحد مع عقل جماعي موحد
that was making decisions.
هو الذي يتخذ القرارات
When I look back, I think that experience really ended up determining
عندما أنظر إلى الخلف أظن أن تلك التجربة انتهت بلعب دورا هاما
what I've worked on for most of my career.
في العمل الذي عملت فيه معظم مسيرتي المهنية
I'm a computer scientist,
أنا عالمة حاسوب
and the field that I work in is artificial intelligence.
و المجال الذي أعمل به هو الذكاء الإصطناعي
And a key theme in AI
والموضوع الأساسي بالذكاء الإصطناعي
is being able to understand intelligence by creating our own computational systems
هو أن تستطيع فهم الذكاء عبرخلقنا نظمنا الحاسوبية الخاصة
that display intelligence the way we see it in nature.
التي تعرض الذكاء بالطريقة التي نراها بها في الطبيعة
Now, most popular views of AI, of course, come from science fiction and the movies,
حاليا، وجة نظر الناس للذكاء الإصطناعي تأتي غالبا من الخيال العلمي والأفلام
and I'm personally a big Star Wars fan.
وأنا شخصيا من أكبر المعجبين بـ"حرب النجوم"
But that tends to be a very human-centric view of intelligence.
و لكنه مفهوم يتمحور حول وجهة نظر الإنسان للذكاء
When you think of a fish school,
عندما تفكر بمدرسة السمك
or when I think of a flock of starlings,
أو عندما أفكر بسرب من طيور الزرزور
that feels like a really different kind of intelligence.
ذلك يبدو كأنه ذكاء مختلف للغاية
For starters, any one fish is just so tiny
أولا، كل سمكة واحدة هي صغيرة جداً
compared to the sheer size of the collective,
مقارنة بالحجم الهائل للجماعة،
so it seems that any one individual
لذلك فإنه يبدو أن كل فرد واحد
would have a really limited and myopic view of what's going on,
ستكون له نظرة محدودة و ضيقة لما يحدث،
and intelligence isn't really about the individual
و الذكاء ليس حقا حول الفرد
but somehow a property of the group itself.
و إنما بطريقة ما، فهو ملكية مشتركة للمجموعة نفسها.
Secondly, and the thing that I still find most remarkable,
ثانيا، الشئ الذي أراه أكثرهم تميزاً،
is that we know that there are no leaders supervising this fish school.
هو أننا نعرف أنه لا يوجد قادة يراقبون مدرسة الأسماك هذه
Instead, this incredible collective mind behavior
وبدلاً من ذلك سلوك العقل الجماعي المذهل هذا
is emerging purely from the interactions of one fish and another.
ينشأ على نحو محض من تفاعلات الأسماك الواحدة مع الأخرى
Somehow, there are these interactions or rules of engagement
بطريقة ما توجد تلك التفاعلات أو قواعد الاختلاط
between neighboring fish
بين الأسماك المجاورة
that make it all work out.
التي تجعلها تنجح
So the question for AI then becomes,
إذاً، السؤال عن الذكاء الإصطناعي يصبح
what are those rules of engagement that lead to this kind of intelligence,
ما هي قواعد الإندماج التي تؤدي لهذا النوع من الذكاء
and of course, can we create our own?
و طبعا، هل يمكننا أن نصنع الذكاء الخاص بنا؟
And that's the primary thing that I work on with my team in my lab.
و هذا هو الشيء الأساسي الذي أعمل عليه مع فريقي بالمختبر
We work on it through theory,
نعمل عليه عن طريق النظرية
looking at abstract rule systems
ننظر إلى نظم القواعد الصارمة
and thinking about the mathematics behind it.
ونفكر في الرياضيات وراءها
We also do it through biology, working closely with experimentalists.
وأيضا نفحصها من خلال علم الأحياء حيث نعمل مع المختبرين
But mostly, we do it through robotics,
ولكن غالبا ما نفحصها من خلال علم الآليات
where we try to create our own collective systems
حيث نحاول أن نبتكر نُظمنا المجمعة
that can do the kinds of things that we see in nature,
التي لها القدرة على عمل الأشياء التي نراها في الطبيعة
or at least try to.
أو على الأقل نحاول
One of our first robotic quests along this line
واحدة من أول المعضلات التي واجهتنا في هذا العمل
was to create our very own colony of a thousand robots.
هي أن نبني مستعمرتنا الخاصة من الآليين
So very simple robots,
آلات بسيطة جدا
but they could be programmed to exhibit collective intelligence,
ولكن يمكن برمجتها لتستقبل الذكاء المُجمَّع
and that's what we were able to do.
وهذا ما تمكننا من عمله
So this is what a single robot looks like.
وهذا مايبدو عليه آلي واحد
It's quite small, about the size of a quarter,
هو صغير نوعا ما في حجم عملة ربع - الدولار -
and you can program how it moves,
ويمكنك برمجة كيف يتحرك
but it can also wirelessly communicate with other robots,
ولكن يمكنه أيضا أن يتصل مع الآلات الأخرى لاسلكيا
and it can measure distances from them.
ويمكنه قياس المسافة بينهم
And so now we can start to program exactly an interaction,
فنتمكن من بدء برمجة تفاعل
a rule of engagement between neighbors.
وقانون للاتصال بين المتجاورين منهم
And once we have this system,
في اللحظة التي نحصل فيها على هذا النظام
we can start to program many different kinds of rules of engagement
سنتمكن من برمجة أنواع مختلفة من الاتصال
that you would see in nature.
ويمكنكم رؤيتها في الطبيعة
So for example, spontaneous synchronization,
فمثلاً، التزامن العشوائي
how audiences are clapping and suddenly start all clapping together,
كيف أن الجمهور يصفق وفجأة يبدأ الكل بالتصفيق معا
the fireflies flashing together.
وأن يومض الناموس المضئ معاً
We can program rules for pattern formation,
يمكننا برمجة قوانين لتشكيل أنماط
how cells in a tissue
كيف للخلايا في رابطة
determine what role they're going to take on
أن تحدد الدور الذي ستشغله
and set the patterns of our bodies.
وأن تشكل تلك الأشكال في أجسامنا
We can program rules for migration,
يمكننا برمجة قوانين للهجرة
and in this way, we're really learning from nature's rules.
وبهذه الطريقة، نحن نتعلم من قوانين الطبيعة
But we can also take it a step further.
ولكن يمكننا أيضا أن نخطو بالأمر خطوة أكبر
We can actually take these rules that we've learned from nature
يمكننا أن نأخذ تلك القوانين؛ التي تعلمناها من الطبيعة
and combine them and create entirely new collective behaviors
ونمزجهم لابتكار سلوكيات مجمعة جديدة تماماً
of our very own.
من صنعنا نحن
So for example,
فمثلا:
imagine that you had two different kinds of rules.
تخيا أن عندك نوعين من القوانين
So your first rule is a motion rule
أول قانون هو قانون الحركة
where a moving robot can move around other stationary robots.
حيث الآلي المتحرك يمكنه الحركة حول آخر موضعي
And your second rule is a pattern rule
والقانون الثاني قانون نمطي
where a robot takes on a color based on its two nearest neighbors.
حيث يأخذ الآلي لون، مبني على أساس الأثنين المجاورين له
So if I start with a blob of robots in a little pattern seed,
فإذا بدأت بمجموعة من الآليات، في
it turns out that these two rules are sufficient for the group
فتصبح تلك القاعدتان كافيتان للمجموعة
to be able to self-assemble a simple line pattern.
لتصب قادرة على ترتيب نفسها ذاتياً في نمط خطي
And if I have more complicated pattern rules,
وإذا كان عندي قوانين أكثر لأنماط معقدة
and I design error correction rules,
وصممت قوانين لتصليح الأخطاء،
we can actually create really, really complicated self assemblies,
فسنتمكن فعلاً من خلق مجموعات ترتب نفسها ذاتياً
and here's what that looks like.
وهذا ما ستبدو عليه
So here, you're going to see a thousand robots
فهنا، سترون ألف آلي
that are working together to self-assemble the letter K.
يعملون معا ليترتبوا ذاتيا لتكوين الحرف "k"
The K is on its side.
"k" على جانبها
And the important thing is that no one is in charge.
والشئ المهم أنه لا يوجد شخص مسئول
So any single robot is only talking to a small number of robots nearby it,
فكل آلي يتحدث فقط مع عدد قليل من الآليين بجواره
and it's using its motion rule to move around the half-built structure
ويستخدم قوانين الحركة الخاصة به ليتحرك حول البناء نصف المكتمل
just looking for a place to fit in based on its pattern rules.
باحثا عن مكان له بناءاً على قوانين النمط
And even though no robot is doing anything perfectly,
وعلى الرغم من أنه ليس هناك آلي واحد يقوم بمهمته على أكمل وجه
the rules are such that we can get the collective to do its goal
القوانين هي أن نجعل المجموعة كلها تصل لهدفها
robustly together.
بقوة سوياً
And the illusion becomes almost so perfect, you know --
وتصبح الصورة كاملةً إلى حدٍ ما تعرفون--
you just start to not even notice that they're individual robots at all,
أنكم قد لا تلاحظون حتى أنهم آلات مفردة
and it becomes a single entity,
وتصبح كياناً واحداً
kind of like the school of fish.
نوعاً ما مثل مدرسة الأسماك
So these are robots and rules in two dimensions,
تلك هي الآليات والقوانين في بعدين
but we can also think about robots and rules in three dimensions.
ولكن يمكننا أيضا التفكير ف الآليات والقوانين بأبعادٍ ثلاثة
So what if we could create robots that could build together?
فماذا لو استطعنا صنع آليات يمكنهم البناء سوياً؟
And here, we can take inspiration from social insects.
هنا يمكننا أن نستلهم من الحشرات الاجتماعية
So if you think about mound-building termites
فإذا فكرنا في النمل الأبيض الباني للتلال
or you think about army ants,
او فكرنا في نمل الجيوش
they create incredible, complex nest structures out of mud
فهم يخلقون تصاميم لا تُصَدَق لمستعمراتهم من الطين
and even out of their own bodies.
وربما من أجسامهم
And like the system I showed you before,
وكالمناذج التي رأيتكم إياها من قبل
these insects actually also have pattern rules
تلك الحشرات عندهم قوانين للأنماط
that help them determine what to build,
تساعدهم على تحديد ماذا سيبنون
but the pattern can be made out of other insects,
ولكن هذه التصاميم يمكن بناءها من حشرات أخرى
or it could be made out of mud.
أو أن تُبنى من الطين
And we can use that same idea to create rules for robots.
ويمكننا استخدام نفس الفكرة لخلق قوانين للآليين
So here, you're going to see some simulated robots.
هنا يمكننا أن نرى محاكاة لبعض لآليين
So the simulated robot has a motion rule,
وهذه المحاكاة لها قوانين حركة
which is how it traverses through the structure,
والتي تتحرك بها عبر البناء
looking for a place to fit in,
باحثةً عن مكان لها
and it has pattern rules where it looks at groups of blocks
ولها قوانين نمطية تنظر من خلالها عبر مجموعة من قطع البناء
to decide whether to place a block.
لتقرر أين ستضع هذه القطعة
And with the right motion rules and the right pattern rules,
ومن خلال قوانين الحركة الصحيحة، وقوانين الأنماط الصحيحة
we can actually get the robots to build whatever we want.
يمكننا فعلاً أن نجعل الآليين يبنون أي شئ نريده
And of course, everybody wants their own tower.
وبالطبع كل فرد يريد أن يبني برجه الخاص
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So once we have these rules,
فور استنتاجنا لتلك القوانين
we can start to create the robot bodies that go with these rules.
سيمكننا أن نبني آليين لتتبع تلك القوانين
So here, you see a robot that can climb over blocks,
فهنا،يمكنكم رؤية آلي يمكنه تسلق قطع البناء
but it can also lift and move these blocks
بل أيضاً أن يرفع وينقل تلك القطع
and it can start to edit the very structure that it's on.
ويمكنها البدء في تعديل البناء الأصلي لها
But with these rules,
ولكن بهذه القوانين
this is really only one kind of robot body that you could imagine.
يمكنك تخيل شكل واحد فقط لجسم الآلي
You could imagine many different kinds of robot bodies.
يمكنك تخيل عدة أشكال لأجسام الآليين
So if you think about robots that maybe could move sandbags
فإذا فكرت بآليين يمكنهم تحريك أكياس الرمال
and could help build levees,
ويمنها المساعدة في بناء الأرصفة
or we could think of robots that built out of soft materials
أو نفكر في آليين مصنوعين من مواد لينة
and worked together to shore up a collapsed building --
ويعملون معا لدعم مبنى منهار
so just the same kind of rules in different kinds of bodies.
فنفس نوع القوانين في أنواع أجسام مختلفة
Or if, like my group, you are completely obsessed with army ants,
أو، مثل فريقي، أنت مهووس بنمل الجيوش
then maybe one day we can make robots that can climb over literally anything
فربما يوما ما سنتمكن من صنع آليين يمكنهم تسلق أي شئ
including other members of their tribe,
حتى لو كان فردا آخر من نفس قبيلتهم
and self-assemble things out of their own bodies.
وأشياء تخرج من أجسامهم تبني نفسها ذاتياً
Once you understand the rules,
عندما تفهم القوانين
just many different kinds of robot visions become possible.
تصبح رؤية أنواع مختلفة من الآليين ممكنة
And coming back to the snorkeling trip,
بالعودة إلى رحلة الغوص
we actually understand a great deal about the rules that fish schools use.
نحن نفهم الكثير عن القوانين التي تسخدمها مدارس الأسماك
So if we can invent the bodies to go with that,
فإذا تمكننا من اختراع الأجسام التي تتماشى مع ذلك
then maybe there is a future
فربما يكون مستقبلاً
where I and my group will get to snorkel with a fish school of our own creation.
فيه نتمكن أن وفريقي من الغوص مع أسماك من صنعنا
Each of these systems that I showed you
كل من هذه النظم التي أريتكم إياها
brings us closer to having the mathematical and the conceptual tools
تقرِّبنا من الحصول على أدوات رياضية ومعنوية
to create our own versions of collective power,
لصنع نسخنا من القوى الجماعية
and this can enable many different kinds of future applications,
وهذا سيتيح أنواع كثيرة من التطبيقات المستقبلية
whether you think about robots that build flood barriers
سواء نت تفكر في آليين يبنون السدود
or you think about robotic bee colonies that could pollinate crops
أو تفكر في خلايا نحل آلية لتلقيح المحاصيل
or underwater schools of robots that monitor coral reefs,
أو مدارس آلية تحت مائية تراقب حركة الشعب المرجانية
or if we reach for the stars and we thinking about programming
فإذا وصلنا لمستوى النجوم، ونفكر في برمجة
constellations of satellites.
أبراج الأقمار الصناعية
In each of these systems,
في كل هذه النُظُم
being able to understand how to design the rules of engagement
أن نفهم كيف نصمم قوانين الاتصال
and being able to create good collective behavior
وأن نتمكن من خلق قوانين للسلوك الجماعي
becomes a key to realizing these visions.
تصبح مفتاحا لأن نحقق هذه الرؤى
So, so far I've talked about rules for insects and for fish
حتى الآن، تكلمت عن قوانين الحشرات والأسماك
and for robots,
والآليين
but what about the rules that apply to our own human collective?
ولكن ماذا عن القوانين المنطبقة على نظامنا الإنساني؟
And the last thought that I'd like to leave you with
الفكرة الأخيرة التي أحب أن أترككم معها
is that science is of course itself
هي أن العلم في ذاته، طبعا،
an incredible manifestation of collective intelligence,
مظهر رائع للذكاء الجماعي
but unlike the beautiful fish schools that I study,
ولكن على عكس مدرسة الأسماك الرائعة التي أدرسها
I feel we still have a much longer evolutionary path to walk.
أشعر أنه مازال أمامنا طريق تطوري أطول بكثير لنسلك
So in addition to working on improving the science of robot collectives,
لذا بجانب عملنا على تطوير علم الآليين الجماعيين
I also work on creating robots and thinking about rules
فأنا أعمل أيضاً على خلق آليين والتفكير في قوانين
that will improve our own scientific collective.
تطور من نظامنا نحن الجماعي
There's this saying that I love:
هناك قول أحبه:
who does science determines what science gets done.
من يقوم بالعلم هو الذي يحدد ما يقوم به العلم
Imagine a society
تخيل مجتمع
where we had rules of engagement
عندنا فيه قوانين للاتصال
where every child grew up believing that they could stand here
حيث يكبر كل طفل مقتنعاً أنه يمكنه الوقوف هنا
and be a technologist of the future,
وأن يكون التقني المتخصص في المستقبل
or where every adult
أو حيث كل بالغ
believed that they had the ability not just to understand but to change
يصدق أن عنده إمكانية ليس فقط الفهم بل التغيير
how science and technology impacts their everyday lives.
كيف العلم والتكنولوجيا تؤثرعلى حياتهم اليومية
What would that society look like?
كيف سيبدو هذا المجتمع؟
I believe that we can do that.
أنا أصدق أنه يمكننا القيام بهذا
I believe that we can choose our rules,
أؤمن أنه يمكننا أن نختار قوانيننا
and we engineer not just robots
و نصمم ليس فقط الآليين
but we can engineer our own human collective,
و إنما نصمم نظامنا الإنسانس الاجتماعي
and if we do and when we do, it will be beautiful.
وإذا فعلنا هذا، ومتى فعلناه سيكون شيئا رائعاً
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)